<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Strength out of vveaknesse. Or, The finall and absolute plea of Lieutenant-Col. John Lilburn, prisoner in the Tower of London, against the present ruling power siting at Westminster. Being an epistle writ by him, Sep. 30. 1649. to his much honored and highly esteemed friend, Master John Wood, Mr. Robert Everard, ... whose names are subscribed Aug. 20. 1649. to that excellent peece, entituled The Levellers (falsly so called) vindicated; being the stated case of the late defeated Burford troops. And to Charles Collins, Anthony Bristlebolt, ... whose names are subscribed, August 29. 1649. to that choicest of peeces, entituled An out-cry of the young-men and apprentices of London, after the lost fundamentall-lawes and liberties of England. Which said plea or epistle, doth principally contein the substance of a conference, betwixt Master Edmond Prideaux, the (falsly so called) attorney-generall, and Lievetenant-Colonell John Lilburne, upon Friday the 14 of September 1649. at the chamber of the said Mr. Prideaux, in the Inner-Temple.</title>
            <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 102 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88254</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2182</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E575_18</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204577</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864050</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864050</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116269</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88254)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116269)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 88:E575[18])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Strength out of vveaknesse. Or, The finall and absolute plea of Lieutenant-Col. John Lilburn, prisoner in the Tower of London, against the present ruling power siting at Westminster. Being an epistle writ by him, Sep. 30. 1649. to his much honored and highly esteemed friend, Master John Wood, Mr. Robert Everard, ... whose names are subscribed Aug. 20. 1649. to that excellent peece, entituled The Levellers (falsly so called) vindicated; being the stated case of the late defeated Burford troops. And to Charles Collins, Anthony Bristlebolt, ... whose names are subscribed, August 29. 1649. to that choicest of peeces, entituled An out-cry of the young-men and apprentices of London, after the lost fundamentall-lawes and liberties of England. Which said plea or epistle, doth principally contein the substance of a conference, betwixt Master Edmond Prideaux, the (falsly so called) attorney-generall, and Lievetenant-Colonell John Lilburne, upon Friday the 14 of September 1649. at the chamber of the said Mr. Prideaux, in the Inner-Temple.</title>
                  <author>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657.</author>
                  <author>Prideaux, Edmond, Sir, d. 1659.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 25, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed 1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octo: published before his triall 6 Oct".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lilburne, John, 1614?-1657 --  Imprisonment.</term>
               <term>Levellers (falsly so called) vindicated.</term>
               <term>Young-mens and the apprentices outcry.</term>
               <term>Civil rights --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Detention of persons --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prisoners --  Legal status, laws, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Levellers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116269:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Strength <hi>out of</hi> VVeakneſſe.</p>
            <p>OR, The finall and abſolute Plea of <hi>Lieutenant-Col. John Lilburn,</hi> priſoner in the Tower of <hi>London,</hi> againſt the preſent Ruling Power ſiting at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being an Epiſtle writ by him, <hi>Sep.</hi> 30. 1649. To his much honored and highly eſteemed Friend, Maſter <hi>John Wood,</hi> Mr. <hi>Robert Everard,</hi> Mr. <hi>Humphrey Marſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>Hugh Huſt,</hi> Mr. <hi>William Huchinſon,</hi> Mr. <hi>James Carpen;</hi> whoſe names are ſubſcribed <hi>Aug.</hi> 20. 1649. to that <hi>excellent Peece,</hi> entituled <hi>The Levellers (falſly ſo called) Vindicated;</hi> being the ſtated Caſe of the late defeated <hi>Burford</hi> Troops. And to <hi>Charles Collins, Anthony Briſtlebolt, William Trabret, Stephen Smith, Edward Walgrave, Thomas Friſby, Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Stanley, William White, Nicholas Blowd,</hi> and <hi>John Floyd;</hi> whoſe names are ſubſcribed, <hi>Auguſt</hi> 29. 1649. to that <hi>choiceſt of Peeces,</hi> Entituled <hi>An Out-Cry of the Young-men and Apprentices of London, after the loſt fundamentall-Lawes and Liberties of England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which ſaid <hi>Plea</hi> or <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> doth principally contein the ſubſtance of a Conference, betwixt Maſter <hi>Edmond Prideaux,</hi> the (falſly ſo called) <hi>Attorney-Generall,</hi> and <hi>Lievetenant-Colonell John Lilburne,</hi> upon <hi>Friday</hi> the 14 of <hi>September</hi> 1649. at the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the ſaid Mr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> in the <hi>Inner-Temple.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSALME 8.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Out of the Mouth of Babes and Sucklings haſt thou Ordained Strength, becauſe of thine Enemies, that thou mighteſt ſtill the Enemy and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venger.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>MAT. 10.19.20.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>But when they deliver you up, take no thought how or what you ſhall ſpeake; for it ſhall be given you in that ſame houre what yee ſhall ſpeake: For it is not yee that ſpeake, but the Spirit of your Father that ſpeaketh in you.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:116269:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen, and loving Frinds,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Know no men in <hi>England</hi> that in my owne Spirit I more highly prize and honour then your ſelves, for your Parts in making, &amp; Mettle in ſubſcribing the two fore-mentioned Diſcourſes; which, without flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, appeares to mee <hi>to be two of the moſt ſenſible and choice Peeces, for the preſent times, that ever I did ſee with mine eyes;</hi> and for which, in my opinion, <hi>the honeſt plaine-hearted men of <hi>England</hi> are as much oblieged to you, as poſſibly they can be to men for two Papers:</hi> at the laſt of which I heare (in eſpeciall manner) the great men in Power are exceeding mad; and well may they, for in the <hi>11</hi> page of the <hi>Out-Cry,</hi> you have light upon <hi>the true Remedy of all</hi> England<hi>'s Maladies, and the reall-Way to its Peace and Freedom</hi> (viz.) <hi>The chooſing out of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents amongſt thoſe that yet are honeſt in the Army and Countrey, to promote the calling of a new Parliament, upon the Principles of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per called</hi> The Agreement of the People, <hi>Dated 1</hi> May <hi>1649.</hi> which they hate above all things in the <hi>Earth</hi> and <hi>Hell</hi> beſides; as that which unavoyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably will put a certain Period to their hatefull and moſt deteſtable, new, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtart-Tyranny; and therefore to affright you from the farther proſequuting of thoſe excellent things you there promiſe, they have granted a Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion (as it is ſaid) to ſet up a <hi>Bull-begger,</hi> called <hi>A Court of Oyer and Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miner,</hi> to try you for your Lives, which Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion (of <hi>Oyer and Terminer</hi>) <hi>is a meere Innovation upon our Liberties and Freedoms, and againſt the tenor of</hi> Magna Charta, and ſo <hi>void and null in Law, by the very letter of the late Act that aboliſhed the Star-Chamber,</hi> as at the latter end hereof I intend more fully and particularly to ſhew you; it being an <hi>Extraordinary, Surprizing, Partiall, Prae-judging manner of Tryall;</hi> and therefore <hi>null, void,</hi> and <hi>illegall;</hi> being of the ſame Nature with the Houſe of <hi>Lords,</hi> the <hi>High Court of Juſtice,</hi> and the <hi>Councell of State;</hi> and therefore the ſame Arguments that I uſed againſt them, will ſerve againſt this pretended Court of <hi>Oyer and Terminer:</hi> But my main and principall Exception againſt it, you will find conteined in the following Narrative of my late Diſcourſe with Mr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> the nick-named <hi>Attorney-Generall,</hi> which is, That the preſent pretended-Power is no <hi>true-Power, Authority, or Parliament</hi> in any ſenſe; upon the ſtrength of which Arguments, I am reſolved (through the Power of my Lord God Omnipotent) to venter my Life, and all that in this world is deare to me, and therefore out of my indeered affection to you, ſhall exhort you to doe the ſame, as the moſt <hi>juſt, ſafe</hi> and <hi>honorable-Plea</hi> in the World (as things now ſtand) that you can eaſt your Lives upon; The ſubſtance of which, without any intentionall or deſirable wronging of Mr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> thus followeth.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116269:2"/>
            <p>UPON Friday, being the 14. of <hi>September</hi> 1649. I was carried by the Lieutenant of the Tower to Mr. <hi>Prideaux</hi>'s Chamber in the Inner Temple, who when I came there, the Lievetenant went in unto him, and as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive acquainted him with my <hi>Salua Libertate</hi> that I had given him at the Tower, which is now in Print, which I beleeve Mr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> read, and after a little ſpace of time I was called in to Mr. <hi>Prideaux</hi>'s Chamber, who civily ſaluted mee by my name, and I him by his; the reſt that paſſed, ſo neare as my memory will enable me, I ſhall here ſet down without wilfully wronging of Mr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> in the leaſt, who was very civill in his behaviour towards me, though other wiſe ſmoothly cunning in his pretended Examining of me; but to go on, divers of my friend in <hi>London</hi> (it ſeemes) had notice of my going thither, although I my ſelfe had little above two houres notice, <hi>and out of their Affection they heare</hi> (I hope) <hi>to thoſe Principles of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and Juſtice, for which I ſuffer, and publiquely hold out unto the world,</hi> came to ſee what would become of me, and therefore ſeverall of them being in the outter Chamber with me, when I was called in to Mr <hi>Prideaux</hi>'s inner Chamber, my friends followed mee at my heeles, which Mr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> ſeeing, after hee and I had done our Salute, deſired them to withdraw, <hi>which becauſe I was reſolved not to owne his Attorney Generall-ſhip, but meerely to talke with him as a private man, I was not ſolicitous for their ſtaying in:</hi> but the doore, as I perceived, being left open they ſtood there, and I am ſure the moſt of them might eaſily heare mee what I ſaid, for I ſpake high enough, although Mr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> ſpoake with a lower voice, who ſaid to this effect; <hi>Lieutenant Collonel</hi> Lilburn, <hi>I am authoriſed by the Parliament, by vertue of my place I hold under them, to purſue ſome things that doth concerne you, and having taken ſome evidences of conſequence about high matters that you are and will bee charged with; I thought it convenient before a Tryall upon them came, to acquaint you firſt with them to ſee what you would ſay to them, and receive your anſwer about them; and judging it the moſt civill way I could,</hi> I <hi>ſent for you by word of mouth, at which, if ſeemes, you tooke ſome diſtaſte, therefore I writ my war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for you the moderateſt way I could word it; therefore to begin, there is a Booke with your name to it</hi> (which hee handed over the Table to me) <hi>Intituled, An Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment of high Treaſon againſt</hi> Oliver Cromwell, &amp;c. <hi>wherein you lay grievous things to his charge, and I doubt not but you will make them good by proofe, and owne the Booke, will you not?</hi> So after a little pauſe, having ſtood bare while hee ſtood bare, I put on my hat when hee put on his, and pulling out a new booke out of my glove, I ſaid with an audible voice to this effect, Mr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> there is a new booke with my name to it, which is of my owne writing, every line of which (ſaving the Printers errours, which are many) I will owne and ſeale with my blood; <hi>in it you may reade of Sir</hi> Arthur Haſlerigs <hi>barbarous and Arbitrary dealing with me, in Robbing mee, by the Rules of his owne will of my eſtate;</hi> juſt Cutter like, while you unjuſtly keepe mee Priſoner in the Tower of <hi>London;</hi> but Sir, for to returne you an anſwer to your queſtion, which is, whether that booke bee mine or no? I cannot, nor will not, becauſe in the firſt place, <hi>I neither owne your Power, nor the Power of thoſe that impow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed you, which you call the Parliament;</hi> and therefore not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any ſuch man as <hi>Attourney Generall Prideaux,</hi> neither being reſolved to owne Prideaux <hi>Poſt-maſter Generall of</hi> England, and diſcourſe with him upon any Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject hee pleaſeth as long as hee pleaſeth let him make the beſt advantage hee can; and this I will doe for that end that you may ſee I have ſome ingenuitie in me, <hi>and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116269:3"/>am able in any ground in</hi> England <hi>where ever I come, to ſay ſomething for my ſelfe and my ſufferings without dauntedneſſe or amazement of Spirit in the leaſt, at all the ſtormes and tempeſts that it's poſſible to raiſe againſt me<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               </hi> And therefore Mr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> having knowne you many yeares as a gentleman of ſome note, I will upon theſe tearmes (if you pleaſe) diſcourſe with you and bee as civill unto you both in word and jeſture, as you can deſire, and I ſhall (I hope) ſo continue, unleſſe you breake out firſt.</p>
            <p>Well Mr. <hi>Lilburne</hi> (ſaid hee) I ſhall bee as civill as you, as 'tis poſſible for a man to bee with faithfullneſſe to my truſt and place; but I wonder th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t you ſhould renounce the Parliaments Authoritie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; I have knowne you when you have owned even this that now ſits. So hee beckning to me to ſit downe, I told him no I was reſolved to ſtand while hee ſtood, and to ſit downe when hee did, ſo wee ſtood, he at one end of the Ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le and my ſelfe at the other all the time of our diſcourſe; but I anſwered him and ſaid; Well Mr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> wee are, it ſeemes, reſolved to bee civill each to other, and for my part I ſay, <hi>let him hee judg'd an uncivill man that firſt breakes the Rules of Civil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tie betwixt us:</hi> but Sir, are you freely willing to heare mee, and I will freely and ingeniouſly ſpeake to that point of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? I with all my heart Mr. <hi>Liburne</hi> (ſaid hee.)</p>
            <p>Well then Mr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> thus, you may remember the laſt yeare the Perſonall Treaty was hotly going on, which the <hi>Princes of the Army,</hi> thought to bee deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive not only to them, <hi>but alſo to the Peace, Freedome, and Liberties of the Nation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and thereupon there was ſome overtures from them (amongſt others) to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of honeſt and plaine People here at <hi>London, commonly</hi> (but moſt <hi>unjuſtly</hi>) <hi>called Levellers,</hi> to joyne <hi>intereſt</hi> with them for the accompliſhment of thoſe ends wee all (at leaſt in pretence) had beene long ſighing for, <hi>viz. the Liberties and Freedemes of the Nation,</hi> and accordingly <hi>the Principles of the Army</hi> in their <hi>large Remonſtrance from St.</hi> Albanes <hi>of the</hi> 16. <hi>of November</hi> 1648. moſt gloriouſly and moſt tranſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndently Declare, <hi>it was the thirſtings of their Soules to ſee the Peace and Liberties of this Nation ſetled, and that not upon old rotten Principles, but upon the firme and ſtable Principles of Reaſon and common equity, that ſo Juſtice and Righteouſneſſe might run downe the ſtreets like a mighty ſtreame; and Tyranny and Oppreſſion</hi> (as much as humane Reaſon could provide for) <hi>bee baniſhed for ever out of the Land of England,</hi> in which great worke they Declare, <hi>ſo to Act as before the Lord, and to approve themſelves both to God and good men, unto both whoſe Jugements they deſired to ſubmit, abhorring and deteſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng the minding of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or particular Intereſts or Parties;</hi> [See page 6. 7. 8. 12. 14. 15. 22. 23. 43. 45. 47. 48. 57. 62. 65. 66. 67. 69.] and leaſt Generalls ſhould ſignifie nothing to the People (as indeede they doe not) towards the latter end of that Remonſtrance, <hi>they fix upon the things particularly,</hi> that will really make the People happy, which are; firſt, <hi>The fixing upon a ſet and ſpeedy day for ending this long Parliament: And Secondly, For providing for the ſpeedy ſetling of the Nations Peace upon the Principles or grounds of common Right, Freedome and Safety,</hi> viz. <hi>the often and certaine meeting, ſitting and ending of Parliaments, flowing from as neare an equall choiſe of the People as may bee, with other bounds and limitations that might render them more fuſt and leſſe arbitrary then in times by paſt they have beene:</hi> and all this by that <hi>unparralel'd way of contract or Agreement amongſt the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee People; yea, and they alſo there earneſtly deſire, that the good things of thoſe well minded People (or well wiſhers to common good) contained in the Petition of the</hi> 11. <hi>of</hi> Septemb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r 1648. <hi>may ſeriouſly bee conſidered of, and thereby the grievances of the Peeple re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, for their eaſe, benefit and proſperity, that ſo the Parliament may, when it
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116269:3"/>layes downe it's truſt, leave a good ſavour behind them, both to the name of Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aments and alſo of men profeſſing Godllineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Sir, I ſay, there was not only overtures to ſuch kind of ingenious men upon the comming out of the aforeſaid Remonſtrance, but alſo in their ſhor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion dated the — <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 1648. at <hi>Windſor, which exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſeth the Reaſons of their then Advance with the A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>my to</hi> London, they poſitively declare, <hi>that the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Treating with the King, and reiecting all be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter and wholſomer Counſells given them; is no leſſe then a treache<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ous or Corrupt neglect of, and apoſing from the publique truſt repoſed in them, yet not aſſuming to themſelves</hi> (as there in words they ſay) <hi>a ſtanding Power of Judgement (as of Right or T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>) to conclude others thereby, acknowledging that to lye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt properly in thoſe whome the People duly chooſe and truſt to judge for them.</hi> But conſidering that ſuch power, as where ever it is, is committed but in truſt, and hat neither this Nation nor any other People did ever give up their Naturall capacities of common ſence or reaſon, as to the ends and fundamentalls of that truſt: And as for the Parliaments breach of truſt, there being no formall power of man in being to appeale to, in the preſent caſe, they poſitively Declare, They cannot but exerciſe that common Judgement which in their naturall capacity is left to them, and therefore conſidering that the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments then breach of Truſt, ſo tranſendently great, as that it was a totall hazard of deſtruction to that Intereſt, and to thoſe People, for which eſpecially (they ſay) the truſt was repoſed; and ſeeing there is no orderly and open way left for a juſt ſucceſſion of another formall and proper Judicature to bee appealed unto in due time, therefore they there renounced the then Parliament, and with confidence ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed to the common Judgements of indifferent and uncorrupted men, exciting all thoſe that yet were faithfull to their truſt in the Parliament to come out and joyne with them, and in ſuch a caſe of extreamity the) promiſe to looke upon them (not as a Parliament, but) as Perſons materially having the chiefe truſt of the Kingdome remaining in them, though not a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall ſtanding<note n="*" place="margin">and if not a formall ſtanding Power, then at moſt they can pretend to no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer at all, but to govern according to thoſe wholſome Lawes and Ordinances they found in being, at this the Armies finall forcing and diſolving of them, till a juſt and unqueſtionable Repreſentative can bee choſen and ſit, having by this their owne confeſſion no power in the leaſt to make any new Lawes at all, or any Orders to beare ſo much as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended name or ſtamp of Lawes; but they have verified the old Proverb, <hi>that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity makes a theeſe,</hi> for their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe hath made them Tyrants and regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of all their promiſes.</note> power, to bee continued in them or drawne into ordinary Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents; yet the beſt and moſt Rightfull that can bee had, as the preſent ſtate and exigency of Affaires then ſtood; and wee ſhall (ſay they) accordingly owne them, adhere to them, and be guided by them (not in all their commands) but in their faithfull proſecution of their truſt (according to the ſence, will and mind of the <hi>Principles</hi> of the Army, our Law givers) which they there Declare to bee only in order unto (marke it well) and untill the introducing of a more full <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd formall Power in a juſt Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative to bee ſpeedily indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured and ratified by an Agreement and ſubſcription of the People thereunto. O vile Apoſtates, never ſeriouſly to think of this more, after they had Declared, but Cruſh, Murther and Deſtroy all thoſe that effectually ſhall put them in mind of it, which ſhort Declaration is ſo fully fraught with glorious expreſſions of Truth, Juſtice, Honeſty and ſelſe denyingn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe, as that they call God to witneſſe, they did not ſeeke themſelves in their then Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116269:4"/>but were even Reſolved they would not take advantager to themſelves, either in point of profit or Power; but rather lay downe themſelves: That it was enough to raviſh the heart or any ingenious man in the World, and to ſeale it after them, and I confeſſe unto you Sir, it did mine.</p>
            <p>But beſides thoſe Declarations, I muſt truly tell you Sir, upon their forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned firſt overtures and invitations of Conjunction of Intereſts, with my forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned friends the <hi>nick-named Levellers,</hi> I was choſen by them to bee one of their foure Commiſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ners, to goe to <hi>windſor</hi> to Treat with the <hi>Princes of the Army,</hi> who upon the place openly, conſtantly, and avowedly, called the then Parliament; a Trayterous Apoſtatiſed Parliament, that had but the name, and was but the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſe, Shaddow, or Shell of a Parliament, having againe and againe broke and forfeited their Truſt, and confeſſing that thoſe they ſhould pick out of them could bee no Parliament in any ſence, either in Law or Reaſon, but only at moſt a mock Power or a mock Parliament, which th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y ſaid they muſt bee forced for a little time to keepe up, to keepe the People in quietneſſe, as the fiction or ſhaddow of Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, ſeeing the People ſo much doted upon and looked after ſuch kind of outſide things; and this was not only <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etons</hi> and <hi>Harriſons</hi> frequent expreſſions, but alſo Mr. <hi>Cornelius Hollands;</hi> not only at <hi>Windſor,</hi> but alſo at <hi>London,</hi> both before and after their breaking and by force diſſolving your Houſe? to the two firſt of which, if they ſhall bee ſo unworthy and baſe as to deny what now I ſay and averre to you, I will make it good as a Souldier, with my Sword in my hand, in any ground in <hi>England</hi> to the teeth of them both or either of them: and for the third and laſt of which I know if hee and I were face to-face hee durſt not bee ſo unworthy to deny it, but if hee ſhould I could eaſily, by pluralitie of honeſt witneſſes, prove it to his face, and I believe Sir, I might ſafely produce your acquaintance and my by paſt faithfull friend Barron <hi>Rigby</hi> for the proofe of a great part of it.</p>
            <p>Nay Sir I ſay further unto you, That they engaged and contracted with us, as ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly as could be, That they would keep up the men they picked out of the Palia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to joyne with, for no other end in the World, but for the avoiding of a new Warre; for the better, eaſier and ſpeedier obtaining of a new and equall Parliament or Repreſentative, which they Declared, againe and againe, their Soules as much thirſted after as any of ours. And truly Sir, upon this ſcore and account, as the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt and unhazardableſt way that I could poſſibly ſee to ſettle the Freedoms and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Nation, I was willing and deſirous in a crowd, to goe along with other men, (and not to be ſingular) to give the Name and Title of a <hi>Parliament</hi> to their againe and againe Declared <hi>mock-Power,</hi> or <hi>ſhadow,</hi> or <hi>ſhell</hi> of <hi>Power;</hi> and if I did evill in ſo doing, I am ſure my intent was the quietneſſe of the Nation; and my ſin and evill in ſo doing I have ſeen and Repented of, and am heartily ſory for it, and hope I ſhall (have ſtrength enough) for the future to doe ſo no more.</p>
            <p>But Sir, when I cleerly and viſibly ſaw that when they had accompliſhed their own ends, by all their faire and ſmooth Promiſes and Declarations, and made uſe of them for no other end in the World, <hi>but meerly to enable them to bee Princes over the People, and to have their Lives, Liberties and Eſtates at their be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k and Command, and began to challenge a right to Rule over them at their will and Pleaſure; my Souſe began to loath and abhominate them,</hi> for the vileſt and groſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt <hi>Apoſtates</hi> that ever the Sun did ſhine upon; and with the ſame indignation I began to loath their <hi>mock-Parliament,</hi> whoſe <hi>fictionated Power</hi> I thought it my duty (and to render my ſelf faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and upright in my generation) to diſcover to my friends and Countrey-men; which when a Member of the pretended Houſe <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Holland</hi> perceived [in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Court of Wards he took me ſharply to taske] and told mee wee were not able to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116269:4"/>move them, for they had an Army ſtrong enough to ſtand by them to back them, but I told him to this effect, <hi>That I thought they had had Conſciences which would have compelled them to have made good their many ſolemn Engagements</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">ſee thoſe notable inſtances of God's ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance upon Faith and Covenant breakers Recorded in the 9, 10, 12, 13, pages of my booke of the 31 of <hi>May</hi> 1647. called <hi>Raſh Oathes unwarrantable,</hi> &amp; in the 2. edition of my Book of the 9 of <hi>June</hi> 1649. Inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled <hi>The Legall Fundamentall Liberties of the People of England Revived</hi> pa. 16, 17, and in that moſt remarkable Epiſtle of Mr. <hi>James Freize</hi> Merchant, (Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in the Fleete) to the Generall, dated 25 <hi>Aug.</hi> 1649. and Intituled the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers Vindication,</hi> page 6, 7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>and Promiſes,</hi> but ſeeing you have not, nor it ſeemes never intended really to performe what you engaged, but doe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to cheat both God and Man, and then make it good with your Swords; for all your Force and Arme of Fleſh, Mr. <hi>Holland,</hi> I tell you to your face, wee will force you, in ſpight of your teeth, to the one of theſe two things: firſt, either to doe honeſt Actions, though your hearts are never ſo baſe, or elſe, ſecondly, wee will by our conſtant and vigorous endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors for our freedoms and Liberties, put you ſo to it, that you ſhall judge your ſelves neceſſitated, for your own baſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, to run ſuch violent and barbarous waies, as either in a ſhort time ſhall breake your neeks, or elſe make you as abhominable to the People of this Nation, of all ſorts and kinds, as ever men on earth were, and in the doing of this Sir, I tell you plainly, make the beſt or worſt uſe of it you can, I will be one of thoſe herein ſhall leade the Van, as long as I have breath.</p>
            <p>And Mr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> though at that time I knew in a manner, as much of your preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Parliaments</hi> nothingneſſe, as I doe at this day; yet being an Engliſhman, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeredly loved my native Countrey, yea the Peace and Welfare of which I then did, and ſtill do value above my own Life, or the lives of my Wife and Poſterity; &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the danger and miſchiefe that in the eye of Reaſon might probably enſue, by De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring openly and nakedly unto the People, <hi>That all the Magiſtracy of England was broke by the Army;</hi> who had by their Swords reduced us into the Originall ſtate or Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os of Confuſion, <hi>wherein every mans luſts becomes his Law, and his depraved will and forcible Power his Judge and Controller:</hi> I ſay I did not then what ſince I have ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidibly been forced to doe, for, it's true, I did the 26 of <hi>Feb</hi> 1648 at the Bar of the preſent pretended Houſe of Commons preſent a <hi>Petition</hi> or <hi>Addreſſe,</hi> fronted with a title as if it were as unqueſtionable a Repreſentative of the People as could be choſen; but that was out of the conſiderations before premiſed, and becauſe without ſuch a ſtile we could not have had any acceſſe unto them, although our danger was then very great; the Petition is ſince printed, and Intituled <hi>Englands n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w Chaines Diſcovered,</hi> which if you pleaſe ſeriouſly to caſt your eyes upon, you will cleerly ſee that we that made it and preſented it, underſtood the condition of that Houſe, and that we gave them ſufficient hints to underſtand us, that ſo ours, and the Kingdoms ſafety might ſpeedily by them be provided for, without any more ſtrugling, or running any more deſperate hazards therfore. But when we could get no anſwere unto that, I helpt to draw up a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Adreſſe, now in print, Intituled <hi>The ſecond part of Englands new Chains diſcover'd</hi> wherein we ſpoke more plain; &amp; in the laſt page of which, we appealed to the next ſpeedy Parliament, <hi>Declaring this in effect to be, what in truth it is, over awed by the Sword</hi> [and now Mr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> to ſpeake in plain Engliſh] <hi>whoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re. School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyes, and no better, you are;</hi> But Sir, I ſay, the laſt forementioned Addreſſe, touching <hi>Prince Cromwell and his aſſociates to the quick,</hi> hee moſt unjuſtly <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled your mock Houſe,</hi> in effect, <hi>to vote mee a Traitor in generall,</hi> which Sir, as
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116269:5"/>you are a Lawyer I know you know to bee nothing in Law, for it muſt bee a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular act, as aboundance of your owne Declarations declare; that in the eye of the Law, renders a man capable of being taxed with Treaſon, Fellony, &amp;c. without hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring mee ſpeake for my ſelfe or ever calling mee in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o your houſe, although a good part of that day I was at your very doore, ſeene oft, and ſpoke unto by ſome of your Members; yea I am confident of it, my greateſt Adverſaries I had in the houſe <hi>knew I was at the doore part of that very day,</hi> for Barron <hi>Rigby,</hi> from ſome of their Agents, at the very doore ſpake unto me, and in their names proffered mee no ſmall thing, <hi>ſo I would bee a good boy and learn the leſſon they would teach mee, which when to his face</hi> I <hi>ſcorned with the greateſt deteſtation in the World; it was not many hou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es after, till I was in generall voted a Traytor, without hearing or knowing any Accuſer or Accuſation;</hi> which is ſuch a peece of Juſtice, that the very Pagans and Heathen in <hi>Pauls</hi> time would have bluſh't at; <hi>and then the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> although I over night knew what was done and could have runne away, or hid my ſelfe, if I had pleaſed, <hi>which I ſcorn'd; I was ſent for;</hi> not by Bayliffes, Conſtables, or Juſtices of the Peace; <hi>but, as if I bad beene a moſt peſtilent or mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous man, that with my breath had brene able to have deſtroyed an ordinary Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of men, and was hauld out of my bed and houſe, from my wife and Children, by a hundred, two or three, of Armed horſe and foote, and guarded,</hi> as a poore <hi>Algier</hi> ſlave or captiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>through the ſtreetes by them;</hi> although alas, I had never forcibly reſiſted the Parliament in my life, nor never ſo much as committed a ſingle contempt againſt he moſt Arbirary and Irregular of their Committees, but alwaies came at their firſt ſending for me, although the Meſſenger was my profeſſed Enemy, and although I had beene ſeverall times impriſoned for nothing by them, yet for all this, muſt I now bee dealt with [becauſe I had ſinn'd againſt Prince <hi>Cromwell</hi>] as if I had fortified my houſe againſt the Parliament, or Army, or had had three or foure hundred Armed men in it for my guard; when as alas Sir, the Deſigne is eaſily ſeene through, which was no more but this; <hi>Crowell</hi> was reſolved to play the knave, and I ſtood in his way, and neither by faire words and faire promiſes, nor by threats would bee brought over to a complyance with him in his viſible baſe waies, and therefore I muſt bee taken out of the way in the plauſibleſt manner hee could; and for that end hee got mee prejudged and condemned before hearing, and that by a pretended Law, made after the Fact committed, and then ſent hundreds of his Armed and mercinarie Janzaries, who are no executers of the Law, to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend mee, knowing I was of a hot ſpirit, and was in my owne Soule glued unto my Freedomes, for the maintaining of which he hoped I would have reſiſted and ſo ſhould therefore have beene knock's on the head, or runne through by his guard, which for any thing I know hee had inſtructed to that end and purpoſe; which Act if they had done, <hi>Cromwells</hi> creatures would have Juſtified it, and ſaid they had but kil'd a voted and declared Traitor, who being privy and conſcious of and to his own guilt, therefore reſiſted thoſe that came to apprehend him to bring him to a le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall-Triall, for his Crime muſt needes bee tranſcendently great, or elſe the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the Parliament, and the Councell of State would never have ſent ſuch a Guard to apprehend him, and therefore, ſeeing hee is gone let him goe; and there is a good riddance of him, for hee was a ſtiffe and troubleſome Man.</p>
            <p>But Sir (ſaid I) after my apprehenſion, I was by the Officers and Souldiers carried away to the Guard at <hi>Paules</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> and from thence to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116269:5"/>
               <hi>Hall,</hi> and from thence to the <hi>Councel of State,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Gentlemen. I am neceſſitated to acquaint you, that the difficulties accompanying the Preſſe, by reaſon of the late Act againſt unlicenſed Printing, hath occaſioned abundance of faults in this my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Epiſtle, and hath likewiſe been the occaſion of leaving out almoſt a whole page of my Copy, betwixt the latter end of the first ſheete, and the beginning of the ſecond, which hath conſtrained me to inſert it after this manner.</note> as you catil and coming there before Mr. <hi>Bradſhaw,</hi> Mr. <hi>Cromwell,</hi> Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig,</hi> and ſeverall other Gentlement I have known many yeeres together, <hi>and ſome of whom I very much hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> which induced mee to give them more civill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect then otherwiſe I would, and conſidering with my ſelfe, (as is before declared) <hi>that I was condemned before I was heard, without Witneſſes or Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſer, without the leaſt ſhadow of any Legall and Judiciall Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings;</hi> and ſeeing I was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in ſuch a manner, <hi>in terrorem,</hi> and carried to the <hi>Councel</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> to be againe there prejudged, <hi>and it might be to be turned over by them, with all theſe clogs and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judgements upon mee,</hi> to a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all at Law; and conſidering with my ſelfe, that never a Jury in <hi>England</hi> durſt do otherwiſe then condemne mee af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all this (though otherwiſe never ſo innoſent) I had no other rationall courſe left mee in the World, to make any deſence for my life, <hi>or to dye any otherwiſe (which I every day looke for) then as a perfect Scoundrell;</hi> but ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely and poſitively <hi>to Proteſt againſt the Power of the Councell of State,</hi> and the Authority of thoſe that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powred them; which I did to Mr. <hi>Bradſhaw's</hi> face,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116269:6"/>and gave him <hi>extempore</hi> my Reaſons and Arguments therefore, which you may fully read <hi>in the ſecond Edition of my Booke Entituled,</hi> The Picture of the Councell of State, <hi>eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in page</hi> 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 11. which Booke, Maſter <hi>Prideaux,</hi> without anſwering to any of your Interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories (but of my own accord) <hi>I tell you is mine, and I will</hi> (by Gods aſſiſtance) <hi>ſeale the truth of every line in it</hi> (ſaving the Printers Errataes) <hi>with my heart blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Sir, by the ſaid <hi>Councell of State I was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Tower of</hi> London, without any manner of Crime laid to my Charge; whereupon divers honeſt people, in and about <hi>London, old and young, male and female;</hi> yea, <hi>and in ſeverall Counties too,</hi> being ſenſible of the wrong particularly done to mee and my fellow Priſoners, and of the wound their own Freedoms had received, in that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt and irregular dealing that was exerciſed towards mee, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and being underſtanding and well-wiſhing People to the Peace of <hi>England,</hi> were loath to be juſt occaſioners of new Diſturbances in the Nation, to avoid which, <hi>They preſented ſeverall faire, juſt, and reaſonable Petitions</hi> to the Parliament, as you call it, in which they intreated them <hi>not to be too haſty, or too ſuddain in their Proceedings againſt us, nor anticipate the juſt, quiet, and regular Proceedings of the Law, and that wee forthwith might be ſet at Liberty from our irregular Impriſonment, putting in ſecurity to be forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with coming to Anſwer (according to Law) whatſoever could be laid to our Charge;</hi> That ſo <hi>de novo,</hi> from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to the end we may have, before a Juſtice of Peace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſuch a Proceeding in every particular as the Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires.</p>
            <p>And truly Sir, for any thing I know, if that had been granted, I ſhould have abſolutely caſt my ſelfe upon ſuch a Triall, although I then did
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116269:6"/>although I then did (as well as now) know that all your Iuſtices of the Peace, and Iudges of the Law, are no more Iuſtices or Iudges than my ſelfs, or the meaneſt man in England, <hi>either in the ey of Law or Reaſon,</hi> and that all thoſe men that are Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by their Iudgements, in the ey of the Law are meerly murdered and but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chered.</p>
            <p>But ſeing no juſt or rational anſwer could be got to any of their Petitions, but on the contrary, all other Petitions <hi>from the baſe, bloudy, and unworthy Ring-leaders of the pretended Churches that came in againſt us, were hugg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, and exceedingly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced; and unworthy mercenary Imps ſet at work to write baſe, lying, and moſt abominable ſcandalous Books againſt us, to the fiting the People to tear us in pieces, and to be unſatisfied with any thing but our Laves;</hi> and ſeing that you your ſelf was by a ſpecial Order authoriſed to proceed at Common Law, to give us a Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al after we were condemned, and our condemnation by ſpecial letters from the Councel of State, (to all the Sheriffs in England) proclaimed in all the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket Towns thereof; And ſeing yourſelf had, (as I was moſt certainly again and again informed) many meetings with the Judges at Sergeants Inn, &amp;c about out Tryal; I ſay, conſidering all this, I was neceſſitated and compelled to draw up my <hi>Plea,</hi> and publiſh it to the view of the Nation, <hi>Wherein I have renounced your Authority, and fully proved you no more a Parliament then ſo many Thieves upon the high way:</hi> To which Plea (by the ſtrength of God) I will ſtand ſo long as I have a life and being; which Plea is contained in the ſecond Edition of my Book of the eight of <hi>June</hi> 16.19 entituled <hi>The Legal Fundamental Liberties of the People of England revived, aſſerted, and vindicated,</hi> which (M. <hi>Prideaux</hi> of mine own voluntary accord, I tell you) I cauſed to be printed, But as for anſwering your queſtion; Whether that printed Impeachment of <hi>Cromwel,</hi> which you ask me whether it be mine or no, I tell you, I ſcorn to be ſo unworthy and baſe, and ſuch a Traytor to my Liberty, as to anſwer you to your queſtion.</p>
            <p>Whereupon M. <hi>Prideaux</hi> ſpoke to this effect, M. <hi>Lilburn,</hi> As for that irregular proceeding towards you (as you call it) it was from a Parliament, and you muſt know, <hi>That a Parliament is not tyed to the punctillio's of the Law in their proceedings, as other Inferior Courts are.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Unto which I replyed to this effect, but M. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> with your good favor, you are too nimble for me, for you take that for granted which I deny, and which I am ſure you can never prove while you breath; for <hi>I aver you are no Parliament, either upon the principles of Law or Reaſon.</hi> But ſecondly, for Argument ſake, <hi>Admit you to be a Parliament,</hi> yet by your own Principles, and by the Principles of the Law of England, <hi>Law makers are not, cannot, nor ought to be Law Executors.</hi> But thirdly, upon your own Principles I anſwer, and do believe, you have not bin ſo long a Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer, but you have carefully read over the fourth part of <hi>Cooks Inſtitutes,</hi> that great Oracle among you Lawyers, and if you pleaſe to recollect your memory, you may very well remember in ſeveral places of his chapter of <hi>High Court of Parliament,</hi> there he often urgeth and preſſeth, and also layeth down Arguments and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to prove, <hi>That the Parliament ought to be more juſt and righteous in their
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116269:7"/>proceedings, then other Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior * Courts, and ought to be Preſidents of Righteouſneſs and Juſtice to other Courts;</hi> and I am ſure <hi>that Book is publiſhed by the ſpecial Order of the late Parliament for good Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whoſe expreſſions there, f. 37, 38, 39. in the Caſe of the L. <hi>Cromwel</hi> in <hi>H.</hi> 8. time, and in the caſe of Sir <hi>Jo. Mortimer,</hi> in <hi>H.</hi> 6. time, and <hi>El. Barton,</hi> and other in <hi>H.</hi> 8. time, are ſo juſt, excellent, tranſcendent, and glorious, that they deſerve to be written in letters of gold, and poſted upon all the publike places of the Nation, a witneſſes and teſtimonies of condemnation againſt the baſe proceeding of the preſent large pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to righteouſneſs, with my ſelf &amp; divers other</p>
            <p>But Sir, ſaid M. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> Did you not own that for a Parliament that ſate at Weſt-minſter before the Armies laſt coming to London; I am ſure you ventured your life at their command, and to maintain their Authority, and alſo ſuffered much for them at Oxford.</p>
            <p>Its true M. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> if I had not owned the Lords and Commons ſiting at Weſt-minſter, for a Parliamont, according to the conſtitution of England, five, ſix, or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven yeer, ago, and alſo bin ſatisfied in my own Conſcience of the juſtneſs of their quarrel with the King, I would never have ventured my life ſo heartily for them as I did, for I muſt truly tell you, without much vaunting, I fought as reſolutely, and ſerved them (or rather, <hi>the Nation, and its Liberties in them, or by them</hi>) as faithfully as any man in England did, yea, and did more (when I was like to be hanged at Oxford for them) then ever I heard of any in England did for them; for I pleaded to my Indictment reſolutely and underſtandingly, as a man that well knew and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood what I went about, and was reſolved to dy in the juſtification of it, defyingly to his adverſaries. And after my deliverance from them, I took up Arms again in their ſervice, and ſerved them faithfully and heartily, <hi>till I ſee them begin to change their Principles, and to turn their backs upon their Primitive Declarations and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, to make the People free and happy;</hi> yea, and ſee them in their-own perſons to practiſe that that they condemned in the King, and pretended they took up Arms againſt for; which when I throughly ſaw, I threw down my ſword, and could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince be induced to ſerve them; yet I never ſerved againſt them, nor never forſook the Principles that they owned and declared, when they firſt engaged; And as for the Lords and Commons, ſince for neceſſities ſake, and quietneſs ſake, I never ſince diſ-owned them, although I never durſt act under them, eſpecially conſidering I had ſo much in my own thoughts to ſay againſt them, eſpecially the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, who <hi>I am ſure intentionally, were never originally betruſted by the people that chuſe them, to ſit above a year at moſt;</hi> and their out-ſtriping their Commiſſion in length of time, nullifies their Truſt. But Sir, What of all this to you that ſit now?</p>
            <p>Sir (ſaid he) very much; For my ſelf, I am ſure I am as much choſen and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted now as ever.</p>
            <p>That I deny Sir, for upon your own ſingle Principles of the Law, <hi>The Kings ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle death nullifies you, for you were ſummoned, choſen, and ſent, to conſult with him, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou cannot do when he is dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well Sir (ſaid M. <hi>Prideaux</hi>) if you had no more to ſay but the Kings death for the diſſolution of the Parliament that would be eaſily anſwered.</p>
            <p>Sir (ſaid I) let me tell you with confidence, that I am confident it is ſo ſtrong in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116269:7"/>Law, <hi>as all the Law in your brains will never be able to anſwer it,</hi> and if you pleaſe, I will argue the caſe out with you in Law: <hi>You know it was ſo reſolved in the caſe of the death of</hi> Henry <hi>the fourth, and you know it is ſo declared by the Lord</hi> Cook <hi>in his fourth part of his</hi> Inſtitutes, f. 46. <hi>and by the whole ſtream of all the Law-books, and Lawyers of England, without ſo much as one ſingle contradiction that ever I could hear or read of:</hi> But beſides Sir, I tell you, <hi>There was an</hi> UNDENIABLE NULLITY TO YOUR HOUSE BEFORE YOU TRYED THE KING, FOR THE POWER OF THE SWORD HAD TOTALLY DISSOLVED YOU, <hi>So that now you in no ſenſe ſit by the Peoples Choiſe and Truſt, but meerly and ſingly, by your Maſters and Impowrers, the Soldiers;</hi> who broke you all to pieces, and kept out above four parts of five, and only let ſuch go in, as the PRINCES among them thought their ſervants, or did engage ſo to be: and Sir, let me tell you, to my knowledge you your ſelf were at that t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me as much againſt the Soldiers proceedings with you, as a man could be, nor their proceedings againſt the King and Lords you did not like, for you ingaged againſt none of them viſibly although your place of <hi>Aturney General<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> led you out to have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n the chiefeſt man in proſecuting of them all.</p>
            <p>Ah M. <hi>Liburn</hi> (ſaid he,) you are in a great error, neither the Kings death, nor the Soldiers force upon the Houſe doth diſſolve us; <hi>for we now ſit by vertue of an Act of Parliament which impowers us to be a Houſe till we our ſelves diſſolve our ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well Sir, to that I anſwer thus; <hi>your truſt by thoſe that at firſt choſe you,</hi> WAS INTENTIONALLY BVT FOR ONE YEER AT MOST, for by the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall Liberties of England, and three ſeverall Acts of Parliament yet in force, <hi>the People of this Nation ought to have a Parliament once every yeer, or oftner if need require,</hi> and Sir, let me freely tell you, that if the King were an Officer of Truſt, as you have declared he was (and I believe he was) then Sir let me tell you, <hi>that his paſſing of the perpetual Act, was the greateſt breach of Truſt that ever he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in his li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> for which he paid deer enough, for that ſingle Act alone, hath bin the chief inſtrumental occaſion of the Warrs, <hi>and of both the loſs of his Crown and life.</hi> And Sir let me tell you further, <hi>or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou that were choſen and truſted by the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to make them more free, but not leſs free<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and authorized by them to continue in that truſt but for a yeer at moſt.</hi> TO GO ABOVT TO DESTROY BY A LAW THE VERY SOVL AND LIFE OF ALL THE PEOPLES LIBER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TIES, <hi>viz.</hi> CONSTANT AND SUCCESSIVE PARLIAMENTS; And to inſtate in your ſelves by the perpetual Act for ever (if you pleaſe) <hi>an Arbytrary Power,</hi> WITHOVT BOVNDS, LIMITS, CHECK, OR CONTROWLE, <hi>is the higheſt Treaſon (in your ſo doing) that ever was acted, or committed by the ſonnes of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Secondly Sir, you your ſelves have broak that Act to peices, in that you have deſtroyed two parts of three, that by that Act you were to treat, and joyn with to make I awes, nay, and not only ſo, but alſo above two parts in three of the third part, <hi>viz.</hi> your ſelves, by the power of the Sword are deſtroyed, and your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves that remain ſit not, nor Act not in Freedom as a Parliament ought to do, but have your work cut out, and have the Power of the Sword held over you, by which indeed at the preſent to ſpeak properly, <hi>you are choſen and truſted;</hi> they themſelves (I mean the PRINCES OF THE ARMY) having put a Period to your firſt Truſt, <hi>and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtated you by their wills and Swords into a ſecond,</hi> upon their own individual ſcore
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116269:8"/>
               <hi>ſo at the moſt you are but the Armys Parliament, and not the Peoples;</hi> and your Votes or Orders (in any ſence) now, cannot be binding to them; for if in your own thoughts you were not abſolutely inſtated in a new Truſt, but remained in the old, <hi>how come you to have power to ſet up new Conſtitutions, and to alter the Government of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from</hi> a Kingdom to a Common-wealth? which power the People never gave you.</p>
            <p>M. <hi>Lilburn</hi> (ſaith he) we come to have that power by our firſt Truſt, for I hope you will not ſay, but a People for their own benefit, may alter the Form of their own Government in a Nation, may they not? Yes (ſaid I) they may<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but M. <hi>Prideaux</hi> what is that to you? Yes much ſaid be; which way I beſeech you? <hi>I hope you will not ſay your power is abſolute?</hi> Yes but I will ſaid M. <hi>Prideaux.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well then Sir, ſhew me which way you came by it, for your affirmation is a Paradox to me, <hi>for you have confeſſed</hi> (again and again) <hi>you a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e at moſt but a deligated or betruſted Power,</hi> and I am ſure of it, <hi>no betruſted Power is abſolute<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> the People chuſe you, <hi>and yet you are abſolute, I pray</hi> Sir <hi>reconcile me theſe contrarieties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And beſides Sir, <hi>the People chuſe you not in the leaſt to ſet up Commonwealths, but to treat and conſult with the King and Lords,</hi> and therefore your ſeting up a Common-wealth without any ſhaddow, or preſence of power or Commiſſion from them, <hi>is an imperious and yranical uſurpation;</hi> For let me aver it to you, that thought the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may by a common conſent alter their Government (for no Form of Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is <hi>Iure Divino</hi>) <hi>yet none can do it for them but only themſelves or their Commiſſioners, choſen and impowered by them for that end and purpoſe, which your Houſe Sir was never in the leaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But M. <hi>Lilburn,</hi> for all your thus reaſoning, I know you have in times by paſt liked a <hi>Common-wealth</hi> better then the Government of a <hi>King,</hi> have you not? Yes that I have, and ſtill do, <hi>provided it be rightly Conſtituted, from the conſent of the People, with juſt bounds and limitations, that as little as may be is left to arbitraries: but all its Magiſtrates annualy elective, and accountable, and upon theſe tearmes I am withall my heart f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r a C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mmon wealth:</hi> But to have the name of a Common-wealth impoſed upon us by the Sword, <hi>wherein we are and ſhall be more ſlaves then ever we were under Kingſhip, with a ſuprem pretended power held over us, that in their Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal and Fundamental conſtituti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n admit of no boundaries, but judge themſelves as ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely arbitrary; as the Great Turke;</hi> and that they do not make ſuch Vaſſels and ſlaves of us as he doeth of his people, is their Civillity and courtiſie (more then any thing of obligation, or duty) ſuch a Common-wealth as this I abhor and deteſt as the Devil himſelf; BVT SVCH A ONE IS YOVRS, <hi>and therefore I had rather</hi> (as the caſe ſtands) <hi>be under a King reaſonable bounded</hi> then under you, and your new Sword Tyranny, called a Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>But Sir (ſaith he) you have bin very ſtiffe againſt the King, its true ſaid I, but not QVA KING, but againſt his Arbitrary and Tyrannical Will, when he made it a rule unto himſelf, and the People above the Law; I tell you Sir, the ſame principle that led me to hate Will in the King, leads me a thouſand times more to hate Will in you, ſeeing you have promiſed better things, ye abſolute Freedom, and vet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form nothing, but do worſe then ever he did; <hi>by Governing us purely by the Sword and your own Wills.</hi> You wrong us M. <hi>Lilburn</hi> (ſaid he you are governed by a juſt Magiſtracy, for the Parliament votes freely, without compulſion.</p>
            <p>Phy for ſhame M. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> that you ſhould talk ſo againſt your own Conſcience, I know your Conſcience tells you, <hi>there is no Magiſtracy in England,</hi> either upon the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116269:8"/>Principles of Law, or Reaſon: <hi>for the Princes of the Army by their Swords</hi> (Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror like) <hi>have broak it to peices in every particular,</hi> ye alſo your Houſe, and have kept out four part, of five, and at firſt would <hi>let none go in to ſit there, but thoſe that they had liſted in a paper, and had</hi> ſome aſſurance of, would be good boys, and learn to ſay their Leſſon as they their Lords and Maſters would teach them, and then they gave to thoſe inſtructions, to form a pretended Committee <hi>to Catechiſe all that ſince have bin admitted</hi> and unleſs to that Committee they gave good aſſurances (of which alſo the pretended Houſe muſt appro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of <hi>) that they had forgot, or at leaſt laid aſide their Engliſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>meu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and language; and perfectly learned the Armies canting language, or at leaſt were will<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng to ſay after them,</hi> till they have abſolutely learned it, there was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o admittance for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this you know to be true, and therefore M. <hi>Pridea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>x</hi> I WONDER WITH WHAT FACE YOV CAN CALL THIS A PARLIAMENT, who indeed and in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>h are nothing elſe, but the PRINCES OF THE ARMYS SLAVES AND VAS<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>S, and Sir let me be plain with you, I and tell you, <hi>I know you dare as well eat <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>iles, and bite off your fingers ends, as to the purpoſe to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ote againſt their Wills and mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> which if you ſhould do, I know you your ſelves know; <hi>they would purge you, and purge you, again and again, to</hi> SVCH LOATHSOME DREGS, THAT YOVR VERY SELVES SHOVLD AB<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HOR YOVR SELVES: But Sir it ſeems; you judge it better to go hand in hand with them, and to be at their becks, that ſo you may go ſharers with them, in the ſpoiles of the Nation, and in taking the Peoples money from them, and deviding it amongſt your ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lves, then to conteſt with them; and you may ſay it is good being in ſuch a condition; <hi>for you can do any thing, and every thing to any man, and cruſh him to peices and deſtroy him: but he can have no Right, or Iuſtice againſt you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why will you ſay ſo M. <hi>Lilburn</hi> (ſaid he) I am ſure the Parliament hath given up their Priviledges in anſwering mens actions, more then ever Parliament did.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid I, I ſay that which is truth; Its true of ancient time (when Parliaments were often and ſhort) <hi>Priviledging of the Perſons of Parli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>men from arreſts, might have ſome pretence of Juſtice and Equity in it,</hi> BUT IN AN ETERNAL, OR A NINE YEERS PARLIAMENT, IT CAN HAVE NONE; and I tell you Sir, I know it is enough to deſtroy a man (though a Member of your Houſe do him never ſo much wrong) if he do but ſo much as open his lips againſt him: and how many men have bin undone for complaining of the villanous and viſible baſeneſs of your Members? <hi>It is as the ſin againſt the holy Ghoſt mong you:</hi> And as for a pet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y inconſiderable Member of your Houſe now and then (OF BOON AND CUR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TESIE) to be ordered, in point of debt or the like, to anſwer the Law, Alas, what is it, It is no more then a cheat, for it is nor only before a Iudge of his own making, who with his Under Officers will find tricks enough to ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe their Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. And beſides Sir, The thing that I drive is to ſhew, <hi>That it is an inherent Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple in you, that this is not done out of Right, but permited out of Grace and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor:</hi> this remaining ſtill at the bottome, <hi>That there is an inherent Principle of Arby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarineſs, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nboundedneſs, and Abſoluteneſs inherent in you, at your pleaſure to make abſolute ſlaves of the People</hi> (if you will) <hi>and to make your ſelves abſolutely nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accomptable if you pleaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Why M<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Lilburn,</hi> would you have no Government?</p>
            <p>Yes (M. <hi>Prideaux</hi>) that I would; But yet ſuch a Government as hath not <hi>at the root and bottom of it, all the Principles of Tyranie in the World, to make the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116269:9"/>abſolute ſlaves at the Will and Pleaſure of their Governors:</hi> But I would have ſuch a Government, that is founded upon the Baſis of Freedom, Reaſon, Iuſtice, and Common Equity, and ſhall ſo ty the hand of the Governor, that he ſhall not be able at his Will and Pleaſure to deſtroy the Governed, without runing an appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent and viſible hazard of deſtruction to Himſelf, Eſtate, and Family.</p>
            <p>I but M. <hi>Lilburn,</hi> who ſhall be Iudge ſaid he?</p>
            <p>Sir, (ſaid I) Reaſon is demonſtrable of it ſelf, and every man (leſs or more) is endued with it; and it hath but one ballance to weigh it in, or one touch-ſtone to try it by, <hi>viz.</hi> To teach a man to do as he would be done to. The Sun is demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrable of it ſelf by its heat and light, and ſtands in need of no mans Iudgement when it ſhines, to judge whether it doth ſo or no, or of reaſons to prove it the Sun; Even ſo, <hi>Reaſon is demonſtrable by its innate glory<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> life, and efficacy; and man being a reaſonable creature, is Judge for himſelf:</hi> But by reaſon of his preſent corrupted eſtate, and want of perfection, he is ſomthing partial in his own caſe, and therefore wherein many are concerned, Reaſon tels him, <hi>Commiſſioners choſen out, and tyed to ſuch rational Inſtructions as the Chuſers give them, are the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and equalleſt Judges:</hi> But yet Sir let me tell you, <hi>That a Commiſſion given unto them againſt the Rules of common Reaſon,</hi> IS VOYD IN IT SELF; <hi>and a power exerciſed by the Commiſſioners beyond the Rule of Common Reaſon, Is not</hi> OBLIGA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TORY, <hi>or</hi> BINDING <hi>in the leaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well then Sir (ſaid M. <hi>Prideaux</hi>) the Parliament now ſiting are the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners of the People, and they have authoriſed me to ask you whether this be your Book or no?</p>
            <p>By your favor M. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> you are to quick, for you take that for granted, which I abſolutely again deny, and which your ſelf is never able to prove while you live; and I tell you again. <hi>They are no more a Parliament then I am;</hi> But admit they were a Parliament, <hi>They cannot authoriſe you to examine me againſt my ſelf</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Sir, <hi>I deteſt the returning you any anſwer to your queſtion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Without doubt (ſaid he) M. <hi>Lilburn</hi> you are miſtaken, for I never yet knew it an evil, or illegal to ask a queſtion.</p>
            <p>But by your favor M <hi>Prideaux,</hi> I ſay it is againſt the Law of England <hi>to compel a man to anſwer to a queſtion againſt himſelf;</hi> and your Houſe did ſo adjudge it in the daies of their Primitive purity, in mine own Caſe, in reference to the Star-chamber proceedings againſt me.</p>
            <p>But (ſaid he) They never adjudged the Kings Atrurnies General asking you que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, to be illegal.</p>
            <p>Yes Sir (ſaid I) but they did, for though in the Star-Chamber I was principally ſentenced <hi>for refuſing in open Court to take an Oath to anſwer to all the queſtions that ſhould b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> demanded of me;</hi> the latitude of which oath did not barely extend (if I had take it) to ſuch queſtions as the Court ſiting ſhould demand of me, but alſo <hi>to all ſuch queſtions as the Atturney General (by Order from the Court) ſhould have demanded of me:</hi> to whoſe interrogatories I refuſed to anſwer, a though he examined me by the Orders of that Court; Of which he bitterly complained: and I am ſure of it, The Houſe of Commons, and the Houſe of Lords both, did not onely judge the Sentence it ſelf, but <hi>the whole proceeding upon it,</hi> (anteceding as well as following) <hi>to be il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legal moſt unjuſt, barbarous</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But Sir (ſaid he) You ſent one of theſe Books (meaning the impeachment of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116269:9"/>
               <hi>Cromwel</hi>) down to Colonel <hi>Ayres</hi> at Warwick Caſtle, and ordered the bearer to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver it to him a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a token from you, did you not?</p>
            <p>Sir, I ſcorn to tell you whether I did or I did not; it may be I did, it may be I did not, I will not tell you; but if I did, this I aver to you, <hi>I know no evil in ſo doing.</hi> So he ſhewed me the <hi>Apprentiſes Out-cry;</hi> Sir, ſaid he, you had a finger too in the making this book, had you not? Said I, it may be I had not onely a finger in it, but alſo a thumb too; and what then? but it may be I had nor, and what then? But whether I had, or had not, I will not tell you; But this Sir of mine own voluntary accord I will tell you, <hi>I have mettle enough in me to ſet my Name to all Books I write, without fear or dread:</hi> I pray ſee if you find my name there.</p>
            <p>No Sir (ſaith he) it is not; but it ſeems then, that all books that hath your name to them, are yours: Will you own this impeachment, for here's your name to it?</p>
            <p>No Sir, with your favor, it doth not therefore follow, that all books that have my name to them, are mine, for it is as eaſie to counterfet my name, as to counterfet an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other mans; and it may be it is ſo now, it may be it is not ſo, I will not tell you; but this I will tell you of mine own accord, That I have read the Book, and <hi>there I find the ſubſtance of an Impeachment of high Treaſon againſt Cromwel,</hi> that I delivered at your open Bar, the 19 of <hi>January</hi> 1647. for which you committed me to the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as a Traytor in general. And M. <hi>Prideaux, I</hi> know that you know, at your Bar <hi>I</hi> offered the Houſe upon my life, to prove and make good what <hi>I</hi> ſaid; and therefore, why did not you or <hi>Cromwel</hi> then put me to it? But it ſeems, <hi>he was conſcious of his own guilt, and durſt not do it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But M. <hi>Lilburn,</hi> will you own this Book and make it good now; for it is yours?</p>
            <p>Sir, <hi>I</hi> ſcorn to deny any Book that ever <hi>I</hi> made in my life, <hi>for I never made a book, but upon mature, ſollid, and ſubſtantial d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>liberation conſidering well before hand what it would coſt me; and all the fear in ſuch caſes that I am in, is onely till I have got it printed, that I may keep it cloſe and private from the fingers of your Catch-poles,</hi> and when it is abroad, <hi>I</hi> have part of mine end, and uſe to tell no body, but as many as <hi>I</hi> can of it: and the deſperateſt book <hi>I</hi> ever made in my life, <hi>I was never ſo unworthy to renounce or deny:</hi> and <hi>I</hi> will not ſay that is not my book, neither will <hi>I</hi> grant it to be mine. But me-thinks <hi>M Prideaux</hi> you are uncivil, <hi>that you will not receive an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer when again and again it is given you:</hi> and alas Sir, admit it was mine, what fair or juſt play could <hi>I</hi> expect to fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d now to make good the things contained in it, Seing Cromwel <hi>by his ſword hath diſſolved the Parliament, and ſet up a ſew of his ſlaves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you for a mock-Parliament, that dare not do but what he will have you?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir (ſaith he) <hi>Cromwel</hi> is abſent, and you lay mighty things to his charge; me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks you ſhould not be backward to make them good.</p>
            <p>Sir (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aid <hi>I</hi>) if <hi>Cromwel</hi> were in this room, <hi>I</hi> would tell him to his teeth, <hi>he is a baſe unworthy fellow, and hath under-hand by baſe and indirect means, for theſe</hi> 2 <hi>yeers together, ſought to take awa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my life and bloud, for nothing but my honeſty; and in his dealing with me, hath not ſo much as manifeſted one bit of a gallant man, or that he hath an ounce of Perſonal Valour in him; for a man of mettle, and pure Valour, would have ſcorn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d to have dealt ſo baſely with me as he hath done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well then Sir, it ſeems there is a Perſonal quarrel betwixt you and General <hi>Cromwel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yes Sir, ſaid <hi>I,</hi> He hath made it partly ſo, but <hi>I</hi> am onely Defendant; <hi>and were</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:116269:10"/>he here, I would let him know I ſcorn to give him an inch of ground, but would an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer him upon equal terms in any way he himſelf would chuſe: and Sir, I tell you he is the man, yea the principal inſtrument that hath deſtroyed the Peace and Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of this Nation; yea, and by force of Arms hath null'd and deſtroyed the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, and hath left no Majeſtracy at all in the Nation; for which, he is (upon both the Principles of I aw and reaſon) a Traitor, and ought to dy therefore.</p>
            <p>Sir, ſaid he, I tell you the Parliament by force cannot be deſtroyed; for its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued by an Act, till themſelves pleaſe to diſſolve themſelves.</p>
            <p>I tell you Mr <hi>Prideauz</hi> I have anſwered that already, and ſhewed the fallacy and weakneſſe of it, but ſeeing you will not be anſwered, I will upon your and their own decla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed principals give it you a little more fully. I find in the Armies Book of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alarations, that upon the</hi> 26. <hi>of July,</hi> 1647. <hi>the Apprentiſes of London, and ſome other of the rude Rabble,</hi> (but for a few hour) <hi>forc'd the Houſe with a few threats, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Arms, and yet they never came down, but one part of a day; and when they did come, they did not pick and cull, and keep out five parts of ſix, as the Army hath done:</hi> and yet the PRINCES of the Army themſelves, <hi>hath declared that Act Treaſon, and the Actors in it Traitors; yea, and have declared, that that force upon the Parliament tends to the diſſolution of all Government: and though there was but about forty or fifty of both Houſes. LIKE VALIANT MEN, that ran away from the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vowed diſcharge of their Truſt, to the Army; and left abundantly the major part be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them, who the next day of their ſitting, and the other day after-ſat quietly without the Apprentices force; yet the Army would not own them, BVT CALD THEM A PRETENDED PARLIAMENT, A FEW LORDS AND GENTS<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>MEN, SIT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TING AT WESTMINSTER THAT TREACHEROVSLY ACTED AGAINST THE PEACE AND SAFETY OF THE KINGDOM: ASSVMING TO THEMSELVES THE NAME OF PARLIAMENT, all whoſe Acts, ORDERS AND ORDINANCES<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they declared to be null and void, and not PARLIAMEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TARY, NOR BINDING,</hi> (See the Armies Book of Declarations, moſt full in all theſe particulars, page 49. 53, 54. 67. 82. 100, 101. 106, 107. 111. 123. 125, 126, 127. 134, 135, 136. 138, 139, 140, 141. 143, 144.) <hi>for being Abbettors to that force:</hi> (See Article 4.) <hi>yea, and impeached ſome of the eleven Members as Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors: nay, and the Speaker himſelf in his Declaration, calls their forced Votes, NOT THE VOTES OF THE REPRESENTATIVE BODY OF THE KINGDOM, B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T THE VOTES OF A TVMVLTVOVS MVLTITVDE.</hi> Now Sir, if a little force of the Apprentiſes for a few hours-nutrifie the Votes and Orders of Parliament, and make them no Parliament that ſit under that force, (being far more the major part) <hi>in the place where they ought to ſit,</hi> yea and is ſo infectious, <hi>as that it tends to the diſſolution of all Government;</hi> abundantly much more upon their and your own grounds muſt <hi>a far greater force of the Souldiers, diſſolve the Parliament<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and nullifie all their Votes and Orders, and abſolutely tend to the diſſolution of all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:116269:10"/>
            <p>Sir (ſaith hee) it's very true, there were ſuch Declarations that did declare the howſe that ſate in the abſence of us, that were forc'd to fly to <hi>Hounſloe Heath, to bee no Parliament,</hi> and all their Votes and Orders they made in our abſence, <hi>to bee null and void;</hi> but yet the Parliament was kept on ſoote by our comming back and ſitting; and ſo was not diſſolved.</p>
            <p>Why Mr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> doe you think I have loſt all my braines and reaſon? for the forced Parliament, as you call it, was either a houſe of Parliament, or no hou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of Parliament, but if a houſe of Parliament, you that adhered to the Army were ſa pack of Traytors, ſo voted and declared by them, and by conſequence all the reſt of their votes and Orders were Legall and Binding: But if it were no houſe of Parliament, then there was none in <hi>England,</hi> for your houſe as a houſe never ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journed to <hi>Hounſloe Heath,</hi> but to the uſuall place in <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and if thoſe that met and ſate there were no houſe of Parliament, then your houſe was <hi>ſine die,</hi> and ſo diſſolved, and your coming back from <hi>Houſloe Heath</hi> to ſit againe, could not make it a houſe; for being <hi>ſine die,</hi> and ſo, in Law, diſſolved, you could as a Parliament meete no more, without a new Summons, either from King or People; I am ſure not without a new choice Election, and impowring from the People; and therefore every way upon your owne grounds you are no Parliament, but abſolute Uſurpers, and all your Actions null and void in Law, and you liable to ſevere pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for your Uſurpations.</p>
            <p>But Sir ſaith Mr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> you had a finger in diſperſing this booke of the Prentiſes; for I have evidence that you gave ſome of them away, and that you ſent thoſe to whome you gave them to a place where they ſhould have more, did you not?</p>
            <p>Truly Mr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> I muſt now tell you, you are not civill (nor ſo ingenious a man as I had thought you had beene) thus with cunning tricks to force me to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer your Interrogatories, and without doubt Sir, your braines are not in temper, that you are not capable to receive an anſwer, although I have given you it over and over againe and againe, and told you I am not bound to anſwer you in Law, neither will I; but if I were bound, yet you are no Majeſtrate at all, in any ſenſe, and therefore I ſhould countenance an Uſurper againſt my owne Judgement and Conſcience if I ſhould anſwer you; but yet this of my owne accord I will ſay to you, I have read that booke of the Prentices, and I find no evill in it, but a great many cleere truths and honeſt things; and it may bee I beſtowed a ſhilling or three in them liking the Booke well, and it may bee I gave them away when I had ſo done, and what is that to any man, my money is mine owne, and hee that can pick an advantage againſt me let him doe it; but it may bee I bought never a one of them, nor gave none of them away, but whether I did or did not, I will not tell you, and therefore Mr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> I pray have ſo much braines and ingenuitie in you, as to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend and judge you are Anſwered, and aske mee no more Queſtions, for if you doe I wil vex you, and again I tell you, I renounce your Authority, and thoſe that impowred you.</p>
            <p>Good Mr. <hi>Lilburn</hi> bee not Angry, but give mee leave to bee faithfull in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of the Truſt repoſed in mee.</p>
            <p>Good Mr <hi>Prideaux</hi> your authoritie and your truſters, I both renounce, as a fiction and Uſurpation, and I beſeech you bee not miſtaken in mee, to take mee for a ſilly novice, for I have my braines, wit, and nimbleneſſe lively about mee, which are beyond your abilities to catch; for Sir, I muſt tell you, when I was a ſtripling boy of about twenty yeares of age<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and was examined by Sir <hi>John Banks,</hi> the Kings Attourney Generall, in the yeare 1637. which Sir <hi>John Banks</hi> I owned for a legall
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:116269:11"/>Majeſtrate, as alſo his Maſter the King, and the Judges of the Starre-Chamber, that in that particular ſet him at worke, and at that time I had never beene in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble before, nor never had to my remembrance read any of the printed Lawes and Statutes of <hi>England,</hi> but barely the <hi>Petition of Right,</hi> from which Law alone, and <hi>Pauls Plea before the Pagan Roman Governours,</hi> I had learned ſo much Law for my owne defence, that I then baſtled Sir <hi>John Banks</hi> and would anſwer none of his Interrogatories; and doth Mr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> think, that now at this age, after I have beene learning this twelve yeares together, all the learning that the grand Schoole of experience can teach mee, and read aboundance of the Lawes of <hi>England</hi> through and through, and beene toſt and tumbled againe and again from Goale to Goale, for ſtanding for my Legall Rights; that Mr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> (that I know to bee no Majeſtrate) can baſtle, catch, inſnare, or intrap me, with his often (as hee thinks unawares) asking mee one and the ſame queſtion twenty times over, no i'le war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant you Sir, you are miſtaken; and therefore againe I tell you finally; I renounce both your Power and your Maſters the Parliament, as you call them. But yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this, I will freely ſay to you, that ſo you may know that I am a true <hi>Engliſh</hi> man, that happily loves the Peace and Proſperity of my Native Countrey and have no guilt in my owne Conſcience to recuſe mee of any miſdoings to man, though I muſt and doe ingeniouſly confeſſe, as to God, I have my failings and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmites with other men, there being heere on earth in theſe fleſhly mortall bodies or houſes of our, no perfection: But yet Sir, I ſay as to man, that I may cleerely demonſtrate my inward Peace and my reall affection to my Native Countrey, and that there may bee no pretence of Commotions or troubles occaſioned any more about mee; on that condition that you, that now pretend your ſelves a Parliament, will bee willing in ſix moneths time wee ſhall have a new one, and give good cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onary ſecuritie for the performance of your promiſes, that really wee may have a new Parliament, either upon the old Principles or upon the Principles of an Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the free People (the latter of which abountdanly I more deſire) I will bee willing to remaine in Priſon till then, and give good ſecuritie not to write a line, no nor directly nor indirectly to indeavour any publique diſturbance, and alſo I will ingage freely to ſurrender my ſelfe up to a Tryall at Law before Judges of the next Parliaments making, and plead to the Indictment let all the adverſaries I have in <hi>England,</hi> upon this condition, lay the greateſt load upon me that poſſible they can, or if this will not bee imbraced: then,</p>
            <p>Secondly, as I have divers moneths agoe proffered in the Tower, face to face, to Mr. <hi>Dell,</hi> who hath beene Generall <hi>Fairfax</hi> his Chaplain, and alſo <hi>Cromwells</hi> and who in Intereſt is ingaged with them, being largely as I underſtand promoted by them; and yet notwithſtanding being conſcious of my owne integritie and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſſe, and that upon their owne primitive declared Principles; and believing that the ſaid Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> hath a Conſcience, I will bee willing to avoid any further publique diſturbance, that my adverſaries ſhall chuſe Mr. <hi>Peters,</hi> my already pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked, ingaged and incenſed adverſary, and I will chooſe Mr. <hi>Dell,</hi> which two I ſhall bee willing ſhall bee finall Arbitrators, Umpires or Judges to decide all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of differences betwixt us, unto whoſe finall Judgement (all though it reach to life) I will tie my ſelfe to ſtand: provided wee may have a faire, free, publique and open hearing, indifferently for the accuſer and accuſed; and this Mr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> I deſire you to acquaint your Maſters with, and further I tell you, if you pleaſe, I will give it you now under my hand, and if this will ſerve their turne, or ſatisfie them, well and good, if not; let them doe their worſt, I renounce their Power and bid defiance to their malice.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:116269:11"/>
            <p>Nay further Mr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> that you may know I am ingeni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> and not a dry ſtick, although I cannot owne nor diſcourſe with Mr. <hi>Prideaux Attorney Generall</hi> yet if Mr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> the <hi>Lawyer</hi> or Mr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> as a private gentleman pleaſe a any time to ſend for me, I will at his deſire without diſpute, come to him (if the Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant of the Tower will let mee) and I will friendly and fairely diſcourſe with him an houre, two or three, or as long as hee pleaſeth, even till hee bee weary, upon any ſubject hee pleaſeth, either upon Law or Divinitie, mirth or ſorrow; nay I will bee willing that if Mr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> pleaſe, hee ſhall have preſent ſix, eight, ten, or twelve of his fellow Members the ableſt hee can pick amongſt them, and I will diſcourſe with you all one after another, make the beſt advantage to your ſelves you can of my diſcouſe; provided I may have two or three friends quietly to fit by, to obſerve what paſſeth, that ſo I bee not belyed behind my back when the diſcourſe is done.</p>
            <p>I but Mr. <hi>Lilburne</hi> a man doth not know well how to talke to you, you are ſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to print every thing is ſaid to you.</p>
            <p>Truly Mr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> I would have you to know, I can if I pleaſe keepe a ſecret as well as your ſelfe, and I yet never diſcourſed with any man about my Trade, or any other thing, that ever I publikely made uſe of to his detriment, and I would have you to know Mr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> if any man, what ever, communicate a ſecret in diſcourſe to me, I ſcorne to bee ſo baſe and unworthy, and to bee ſo ignorant of the rules of humane ſocietie, as to publiſh it to his prejudice, or to make any other uſe of it but according to the ingagement made by mee to him, when hee communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his ſecret to me; but Mr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> if any man under the pretence of frindſhip, ſhall diſcouſe with me meerely as a Rogue to take advantage of it, to my detriment, or if any man through weakneſſe, ſhall make uſe of my diſcourſe with him to my prejudice: truly Mr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> in both theſe caſes I will publiſh or otherwiſe, as I pleaſe, make uſe of his diſcouſe with mee, for my juſtification or vindication, and in this I commit no act of baſeneſſe or incivilitie, neither is it in the leaſt againſt the rules of friendſhip or humane converſe, or,</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Mr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> if any man ſhall ſend for me on ſet purpoſe to diſcourſe with me to catch me, as I know you now doe, let him looke well to himſelfe, for I will dreſſe him if I can, and therefore Sir I tell you, I looke upon you as my Anta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goniſt, who againſt my own free will and conſent, have cauſed me to be brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, <hi>on purpoſe to diſcourſe with me</hi> (not in friendſhip but to enſnare and intrap me, and therefore Mr. <hi>Prideaux</hi>) ſeeing I know this, I have ſet all my Guards upon you, and looke to your ſelfe as well as you can, and catch a hole in my coate if you can, for I am in the vaine to diſcourſe with you as long as you pleaſe, and will not give over till your ſelf declare your wearineſſe, and that you will diſcourſe no more, and this I doe aſſure you aforehand, that ſay what you will, I will obſerve it as well as I can, and if I bee like to be in a ſtraite, I will make uſe of your diſcourſe for my owne beſt advantage, yea, and if I judge it advantageous to me, I will alſo print it, <hi>therefore looke to your ſelfe,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>True it is Mr. <hi>Lilburn,</hi> in the ſence you ſpeake, to print any mans diſcourſe is not blame worthy, but juſt; and 'tis true, I am your Antagoniſt, and my place &amp; office leads me out to be ſo, and I wiſh I had no occaſion at this time to be your Antagoniſt, but tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Mr. <hi>Liburne,</hi> I am afraid I ſhall ſhortly meete with you at a place where I ſhall be your Antagoniſt upon more uneven-termes then now I am.</p>
            <p>Truly Mr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> it may very well be ſo, for you muſt needs bee upon unequall termes with mee, when you have at your command ten thouſand Swords to make good what ever you ſay againſt me, and I have nothing to defend my ſelfe withall but this
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:116269:12"/>poore ſingle Cane; and it is true. Mr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> being already prejudged, yea and condemned without hearing; You, who repreſent thoſe you call the ſupreme Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and who by virtue of your being a Member of the Houſe, are Judge of the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es before whom you pleade, as alſo a Lawyer, full of Sophiſtry, and therefore an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equall Proſeq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>utor; in all which reſpects you muſt needs bee too hard for me, if you ſhall bring me to the Bar, before thoſe Judges, to Try me, that are made by your ſelves and others that have already condemn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d mee before ever you heard mee ſpeake one word for my ſelfe: <hi>(but yet Sir, whenſoever you ſhall preſſe mee to doe this, I doubt not but ſo to handle you, that you ſhall get neither Credit, ſafety nor gaine by it,</hi> (for the King himſelf never did the like) But Sir, upon equall termes, unprejudged be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a juſt Majeſtracy, I dare with confidence meete you and all the Lawyers in your Houſe at any Bar in <hi>England, and doubt not but with your owne weapons, not only to baffle but ſufficiently beate you,</hi> but Sir, bring me when you pleaſe, upon all your own, unequall termes, I value you not the paring of my raile, <hi>for, I bleſſe God, I am fitted for you, having caſt up my Account long ſince, and I am at peace with Death,</hi> and I tell you Sir, no man can bee a Slave but he that is afraid to die, which I bleſſe God I am not in the leaſt, and therefore deſire you.</p>
            <p>Well, ſaid Mr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> you will be tried by a juſt Magiſtracy ſhortly. No Sir ſaid I, I deny th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, for of you Try me before any in preſent being, <hi>it muſt bee ſuch a Magiſtracy as</hi> Will the Conqueror, <hi>or the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe tooke away Engliſh-men; Lives and Eſtates with and by,</hi> viz. <hi>his will and Sword;</hi> but when ever you doe it, it will be nothing for your credit or honour <hi>to lay me in Priſon for nothing, and koepe mee ſix Moneths together in priſon without laying ever any pretence of a Crime, in Law, unto my Charge all that time, but deale more Tyrannically with me then the Pagans did with</hi> Paul, <hi>in denying me the viſits and acceſſe of my friends,</hi> nay locking mee up cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſe-Priſoner from the Societie of my fellow Priſoners, robing me of my Eſtate to a great value, without any pretence of triall at Law, as you will reade in that book I gave you, Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerigg</hi> hath done, and yet notwithſtanding deny mee that Legall and Cuſtomary allowance that is my right by the cuſtome of the place where I am a Priſoner, to live upon; yea, and endeavor when you can finde no Crime in me, to hire falſe witneſſes to ſweare againſt me to take away my Life, as is truly diſcovered alſo in that booke, <hi>pag.</hi> 8 9, 10, 11, 12, 13. I ſay Sir, conſidering all theſe things, for you to lay me in Priſon for nothing, <hi>and then Moneth after Moneth for you to lay all the provocations upon me that poſſibly you can to compell me either to ſinke under, or cry out upon your oppreſſion, and when they are more then I can well heare; for you then to p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ck advantage of my c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ying out, and goe about to hang me therefore, weighing all your originall pretences of Crimes for which you impriſoned me, will be nothing for your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or credit, but will be a cleere demonſtration that I was an Innocent, Righteous, Unſpotted man when you firſt committed mee, and that meere Malice was the ground of your Commitment, and nothing elſe:</hi> But Mr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> doe your worſt, all of you put together, I weigh you not, nor value you not; for I tell you Sir, as I told the L. <hi>Heath</hi> when I was arraigned at <hi>Oxford,</hi> for fighting in your firſt Warre againſt the King, <hi>I bleſſe God I have already learned to die, having ever ſince my firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt with the Biſhops alwaies carried my lift in my hand, ready at a quarter of an houres warning to lay it downe;</hi> and I tell you againe Sir, I bleſſe God I did looke round about me, to every ſide and corner of the quarrell that I am in, and did ſeriou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly weigh, conſider and debate betwixt God and my owne Soule, whether my preſent engagement was worth the hazard of my little finger; For, and upon a cleere debate in my own Conſcience, I found it to be worth the engaging of my Life for; it being for the maintaining of that that differs and diſtinguiſheth me from a Beaſt, <hi>viz. for my
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:116269:12"/>Liberties and Freedoms;</hi> yea for the main<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aining of the abſolute Soveraignty of God, and that alegiance, by naturall creation, that I owe him; which is to owne him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone as the abſolute Soveraigne and Law giver by his Will and Pleaſure, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny competitor in the World; and Sir <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> you I am knowingly, deliberately and underſtandingly engaged, and by the gracious aſſiſtance of the Lord Almighty, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo deepely engaged as I am, I will ſpend the laſt drop of my heart blood before I will violate my inward Peace, by ſinning againſt my owne underſtanding, in giving ground one inch, or turning my back upon my preſent engagement.</p>
            <p>But wil not the care of the future well-fare of your Wife and Children prevaile with you to deſiſt.</p>
            <p>No Sir, ſaid I, not in the leaſt, <hi>although I love my wife as deerely as any Man in the world loves his,</hi> for I bleſſe God he hath endowed me with that Judgement and underſtanding that he hath enabled me to looke upon my Wife and Children, but as ſubordinate things to his Will and Pleaſure; and <hi>to looke upon himſelfe as the ſum and perfection of all Good,</hi> who alone, of right, is to be owned, in the diſowning of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, if he require it: and I tell you Sir, what ever you and others may think of me for a raſh man, yet upon a cleere tryall of me you will not find me ſo, but a man that walkes by Judgement, Counſell, and deliberation; yea and that by the Counſell of the greateſt Counſellour that ever was; for I tell you Sir, I am not eaſily ingaged upon any buſineſſe; but, when I am about an undertaking, I looke round about it, and into the midſt of it, as well as all that reaſon and underſtanding my Creator hath given mee will inable mee, and if I find God ſatisfying my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that the ingagement is Juſt and righteous, and that in duty and Conſcience I am ingaged in a kind of neceſſitie to undertake it, let men and Devilſ ſtand before mee in it, I will either through with it or dye in it; and ingaged over head and eares I am at the preſent, and therefore reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lved I am never to looke back while I breath, coſt it what it will, <hi>for Money. Gould nor Honour are none of my prime objects, but ly under me as the duſt of my feete.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>Lilburne,</hi> may not you bee miſtaken in y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur Ingagements as well as other men.</p>
            <p>Yes Mr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> it's poſſible I may, for I aſſume unto my ſelfe noe Spirit or infalibilitie, but if I ſhould bee miſtaken in my Ingagement, the punishment is principally to my ſelfe, but ſure I am in my preſent ingagement, I am not miſtaken, <hi>but am upon as ſollid, clea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and ſubſtantiall a ground, as ever any ingagement I was upon in my life;</hi> therefore if in the proſecution of it I periſh, I periſh.</p>
            <p>Well Mr. <hi>Lilburne</hi> (ſaith hee) I think you have ingaged againſt (and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nteſted with) all the Powers in this Nation, both <hi>King, Lords, and Commons,</hi> have you not?</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> if I miſtake you not, you aske mee if I have not ingaged againſt <hi>King Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ds and Commons,</hi> becauſe they were Powers, to which I anſwer no.</p>
            <p>No Mr. <hi>Lilburne,</hi> I aske you if you have not ingaged againſt all them Powers.</p>
            <p>Yes Sir, that I have and more too; <hi>but not becauſe they were Powers, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they left and forſooke that declared and knowne Rule, by which they themſelves</hi> were to bee Ruled and guided, in the exerciſe of that Power, <hi>for Sir, I ſay no Power on earth is abſolute but God alone,</hi> and all other Powers are dependants upon him, and thoſe Principles of Reaſon and Righteouſneſſe that hee hath indowed man with, <hi>upon the true Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſis of which all earthly power or Majeſtracy ought to be founded,</hi> and when a power or Majeſtracy degenerates from that Rule, by which it is to mee Ruled, and betakes it ſelfe to its crooked and innovating will; <hi>it is to bee no more a Power or Majeſtracy, but an obnoxtious Tiranny to bee reſiſted by all thoſe that would not willingly have man to uſurp the Soveraigntie of God to Rule by his will
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:116269:13"/>and pleaſure<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and therefore it was that l oppoſed the Biſhops and Star-Chamber, <hi>becauſe they left the Declared Law of</hi> England, <hi>their Rule and guide and would have Ruled ever me by their crooked wills and pleaſures;</hi> and either this my conteſt with them was juſt and righteous, or elſe you in the houſe of Commons and alſo in the houſe of Lords, <hi>were a company of unjuſt men,</hi> ſo eminently to juſtifie mee in it <hi>by your Votes O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ders and Decrees as you have done,</hi> which Votes, Orders and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees &amp;c. became grounds, incouragements and incitements to mee to oppoſe the Kings will yee and not only his <hi>but the Lords and yours alſo,</hi> and as for my conteſt with the King and houſe of Lords, <hi>you your ſelves have done more then Juſtified mee in both of them, for you have extirpated the functions of them both, which was higher then ever my c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nteſt with either of them,</hi> for my conteſt with both was cleer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly but againſt U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urpations and as for my conteſt with your ſelves (I meane the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſe of Commons, as it is commonly taken) you your ſelves have alwaies hither toward Juſtified mee in that; for although I have beene ſeven, eight or nine ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall times your Priſoner, <hi>yet hithe to you never in all your life laid any pretence of Crime to my Charge, but alwaies releaſed mee as an Innocent and honeſt man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I but Sir, ſaid hee, that was their <hi>lenity, mercy</hi> and <hi>compaſſion</hi> towards you.</p>
            <p>No Mr <hi>Prideaux</hi> by your favour you are very much miſtaken, for I never craved any from them, but alwaies ſcorned it, <hi>continually ſtanding upon my Juſtification and biding defiance to them, as in my preſent impriſonment</hi> I <hi>am reſolved to the death to doe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>Lilburne,</hi> why may not you as well owne our Authoritie (I meane the Parliament) as owne <hi>Barron Rigby</hi> that is made by uſ: for you have call'd him <hi>Barr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Rigby</hi> once or twice, and I am ſure hee was noe <hi>Barron</hi> till the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parliament made him one.</p>
            <p>Truly Mr. <hi>Prideaux, I heartily cry you mercy, forgive mee this crime or errour and I doe aſſure you, you ſhall never catch mee in the like fault;</hi> but truly Sir to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe it, I muſt tell you I have many materiall things in my diſcourſe to think upon and I conceive this but a circumſtantiall or accidentall one, occaſioned by meere for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfullneſſe; having many things at preſent in my head: but truly Sir, having the other day occaſion to write him a Letter, at a time when my braine was troubled with nothing elſe; <hi>I ſtiled him only Collonel Alexander Rigby,</hi> and if you will not beleeve mee I have the copie of it about mee, which I will reade to you if you pleaſe, which though I did not then, yet becauſe I was unawares catch's upon the hip, take heere the copie of it.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>For my honoured Friend <hi>Col. Alexander Rigby,</hi> at his lodging in <hi>Sarjeants Inne,</hi> either in <hi>Fleete-ſtreet</hi> or <hi>Chancery lainc.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Honoured Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MY Particular obligations to your ſelfe in times by paſt, I cannot but in Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuitie acknowledge have beene very many, and I could wiſh it had beene in my power really to expreſſe them in any other manner then words; Sir, the Reaſon of my troubling you with theſe lines is, becauſe I underſtand your man was at my houſe a few houres agoe as from your ſelfe, as my wife tells mee; therefore, although I had rather bee ſilent then my ſcribling give diſtaſt to a man</hi> I <hi>have found ſo much reality in as I have done in your ſelfe, yet out of the loweſt degree of Civiltie and ingenuitie, I cannot doe leſſe (though I muſt freely let you know, I looke upon you and my ſelfe as now poſitively ingaged in two contrary Intereſts that can never ſubſiſt one by th'othe,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:116269:13"/>without continuall Warres each with other) then tender my hearty reſpects perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to you, and further let you know that I ſhould bee very deſirous (if you conceive it might not bee prejudiciall to your ſelfe) to waite upon you at the time and place you pleaſe to appoint to exchange a few words with you, and ſo I commit you to God and reſt,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours particularly very much Oblieged, <hi>John Lilburne.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>Wincheſter <hi>houſe</hi> 
                        <date>this 24. <hi>of</hi> Auguſt 1649.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>But Sir, I muſt confeſſe unto you Col. <hi>Righy</hi> is a man (ſetting his preſent place aſide) I <hi>have a great deale of cauſe to love and honour; hee hath beene my faithfull and true friend, and I have alwaies, to mee in particular, found him a very juſt, righteous and obliging man;</hi> and in that regard being my ſelfe but a fraile man, may bee like the reſt of the men of the world, and out of partiallity give him (on a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine) a ſtile more then is his due; but as I ſaid before Sir, ſo I continue ſtill beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your pardon for this one fault, and I doe aſſure you, you ſhall not catch mee commiting the like.</p>
            <p>So Mr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> it ſeemes, being almoſt wearied with diſcourſe, takes up my booke againſt Sir <hi>Arthur Haſlerig,</hi> and reads a preparrative to an <hi>Hue and Cry after Sir</hi> Arthur Haſlerig, <hi>a late Member of the forceable diſſolved houſe of Commons, and now the preſent wicked, bloody &amp; tyrannicall governour of</hi> New Caſtle upon Tyne.</p>
            <p>Saith hee in Lataine to this purpoſe, good words would have done well and have beene better Mr. <hi>Lilburne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beleeve mee Mr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> for any thing I know thoſe very words are too good for his baſe actions towards me, as I beleeve you will cleerely find it ſo when you read the booke ſeriouſly through, which I earneſtly intreat you to doe, and then it may bee it will take off the heare of your proſecuting me: for can any words hee too bad for a man, that by his will without legall cauſe caſts another man in priſon, and when hee hath him there indeavours to hire falſe witneſſes to take away his life, yea and robs him of his Eſtate by will and power that ſhould buy him, and his, bread to keepe them alive. So hee ſpake another ſentence in latine, which I being not able to underſtand, intreated him to ſpeake in <hi>Engliſh,</hi> for <hi>I was but a ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh <hi>man, underſtanding no Latine but a company of common words,</hi> and therefore intreated him to ſpeake only <hi>Engliſh</hi> if hee would talke any more, but if hee was weary hee might give over when hee pleaſed, but for my part I was not weary, nor would not give over the diſcourſe ſo long as hee pleaſed to hould it:</p>
            <p>Truly Mr. <hi>Lilburne</hi> ſaith hee, for my ſurious proſecuting of you, the duty of my place requires mee to doe what I doe, and I doe aſſure you I doe not know that ever perſonally I did you any wrong, did I.</p>
            <p>Truly Mr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> at preſent I doe not remember, but if ever you did; I doe not call to mind at preſent that ever perſonally I gave you a provocation, or did you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally any wrong; but it is likely Mr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> when you doe mee wrong, either perſonally or officially, that you ſhall heare ſufficiently of it.</p>
            <p>Whereupon he took up my book, and looking upon it, ſaid to this effect; Mr. <hi>Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn,</hi> without doubt you ſcarce ſleep for ſtudying and writing of books. doe you? Yes Mr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> that I doe, as well and as heartily as you or any man in <hi>England,</hi> and as
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:116269:14"/>or ſuch a book as that is, if I be well in my health and my eyes, and be in the vein of ſtudying, I can mak ſuch a book, upon any ſubject in 3 or 4 daies ſpace.</p>
            <p>I but ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h he <hi>preces &amp; lacremae</hi> in your ſuffernigs were better.</p>
            <p>I confeſſe Sir to you it were ſo, for then you might commit all manner of oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Tyranny towards mee without ſeare or dread of ever-beeing told of it againe; <hi>but Sir,</hi> I <hi>know no man hath ſo much cauſe to uſe Prayers and teares as oppreſſors and Tyrants, for the wrong and injury they doe to other men;</hi> but Sir, this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was the Biſhops old weapon which they uſed to keepe the People in peace with; but ſure I am <hi>Paul</hi> made uſe of his Reaſon to defend himſelfe againſt his adverſaries as well as Prayers and Teares; yea and with it to ſave himſelfe, with it ſet them together by the eares. Act 23.6, 7, 8, 9. But I pray Sir, why did not you your ſelve (I mean the houſe of Commons) make uſe of theſe weapons and none elſe againſt the King? <hi>who I am ſure upon your owne Principles was a legall Majeſtrate;</hi> and therefore Sir, if you believe that Prayers and Teares are the only weapons that Chriſtians muſt uſe againſt oppreſſing Majeſtrates, <hi>you your ſelves might have done well to have led us the example</hi> (for examples are moſt commonly of the ſtrongeſt operation upon the mind) <hi>and have ſuſſered the King (a lawfull Majeſtrate) to have out your throats, without either your Reaſon.</hi> (in your Declarations and Remon: ſtrances againſt him, or your Force and Swords, in Fights and Battells) againſt him, <hi>and therefore Sir, you your ſelves having in your Actions and Practiſe</hi> (which are the moſt forcible Preachers) <hi>made uſe of other weapons then Prayers and Teares againſt the King when hee oppreſſed you;</hi> give mee leave I beſeech you to walke towards your ſelves in you owne ſteps, to make uſe of your own weapons againſt your ſelves when you oppreſſe mee; but I aſſure you Sir, if you will not give mee leave I will take and uſe it, and teach it to bee uſed to the utmoſt of my Power and as far as I am able; <hi>and therefore Sir, it is a vaine thing for you to Preach any ſuch old Popiſh Doctrine to me, eſpecially conſidering your owne is quite contra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y to your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent verball Doctrine; and therefore right or wrong; if</hi> I <hi>doe by you as you have done by others, you (of all men in the World) cannot ſay it is unjuſt in mee ſo to doe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus my true friends I have given you as exactly as my memory will inable mee, the true ſubſtance of my diſcourſe with Mr. <hi>Prideaux</hi> the nik-named <hi>Attorney Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall;</hi> who appearing to mee pretty well exhauſted of matter, fairely and civilly told mee hee had done with mee at preſent, and therefore bid mee farewell, and I him; and comming out into his next roome, wee found it very full of my old acquaintance and true friends, at the ſight of ſo many I could not but wonder, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that the Lievetenant of the Tower did ſo ſurprize mee in time, as is before declared, before hee let mee know of his warrant, that conſidering the framing and writing of my forementioned <hi>Salva;</hi> I had ſcarce time or oportunitie to give notice to any of my friends that lives nigheſt to mee; but coming back to the Tower, the twenty-ſeveneth of <hi>September</hi> 1649. Collonell <hi>Weſt</hi> was pleaſed to ſhow mee a warrant which ſeverall dayes before hee had in his hands, the copie of which thus followeth.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whereas Lievetenant Collonell</hi> John Lilburne <hi>hath beene formerly committed priſoner to the Tower of</hi> London <hi>for High Treaſon and that wee are informed, that there is ſufficient evidence againſt him, for bringing him to his Triall for Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: Theſe are therefore to will and require you forthwith to take into your cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy the ſaid Lievetenant Collonel</hi> John Lilburne, <hi>and him ſafely to keepe in the ſaid Tower of</hi> London <hi>in order to his Triall, for the ſaid crime, of which you are in no
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:116269:14"/>wiſe to faile, and for which this ſhall be your ſufficient warrant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Given at the Councel of State at <hi>White-Hall</hi> 
                        <date>this 19. of Sept. 1649.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Signed in the name, and by Order of the Councel of State, appointed by Authority of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: <hi>John Bradſhaw,</hi> Preſident.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>To the Lieutenant of the <hi>Tower.</hi>
                  </trailer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>And ſince the knowledge of this Warrant, I underſtand they have in Order to my particular Tryal, ſigned at the great Seale (as they call it) a pretended ſpecial Commiſſion of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer</hi> for <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Middleſex,</hi> to which I cannot ſo fully ſpeak, as by Gods aſſiſtance I intend, till I have ſeen a Copy of the Commiſſion, which I hope ſhortly to do, and therefore muſt now crave your favour to ſuſpend the performance of my promiſe expreſt in the foregoing, <hi>page</hi> 2. for a little time longer, and intreat of you to accept this which here already I have writ to you in good part, till more come, <hi>and to look upon this as the ſubſtance of my Plea and defence againſt them, whenſoever I come before them; upon which, by the ſtrength of God I will dye,</hi> for which (I bleſſe his name) I am prepared, <hi>as ſcorning their curteſie, and bidding defiance to their malice,</hi> who are to me no more a Parliament or Majeſtrates in any ſence, then ſo many ſtrong rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing Theeves in the high way; <hi>whoſe Power or Authority, by the Aſſiſtance of the Almighty, I ſhall never while I breath ſtoope unto, or ſo much as hereafter directly or indirectly addreſſe unto, or ſuffer any in my name, or for my benefit</hi> (ſo farre as I am able to hinder) to addreſſe unto; only this I intreat of you, that if I ſhould die in this conteſt (for putting them in mind of their promiſes) that you will improve your utmoſt intereſt, that this <hi>Epistle</hi> may live, and many Thouſands of them be re-printed, and ſeeing by their new pretended Act about Printing they cannot be ſold, they may be thrown a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and given, and ſent all up and down the Nation; So with my true love preſented to you all, I commit you to the ſafe Protection of the Lord God omnipotent, and reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>From my unjuſt and cauſeleſſe captivity in the Tower of</hi> London, <date>
                     <hi>this</hi> 30. <hi>of Sept.</hi> 1649.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your faithfull friend and Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, ſo long as he is.</hi> John Lilburne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>Postscript</head>
            <p>
               <hi>ALL The Petitions to the pretended Houſe, for their Courteſie or Favour towards mee, by any Perſons whatſoever, though never ſo nigh to mee; I totally diſavow, diſclaime, and diſowne, as altogether done againſt my Conſent, Will, and Mind, being abſolutely Reſolved, by the ſtrength of God, to lay down the laſt drop of my blood, in Defence of my foregoing Diſcourſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>October 13. 1649.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>John Lilburne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
